[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
hello everyone and welcome to the stoa
estoa is a digital campfire where we
gather to coherent dialogue
about what matters most at the nice edge
of this moment
and this is the beginning of a
three-part
series of interviews that we're doing
with the philosopher queens
my name is raven connolly and i'm one of
the hosts here with
rachel haywire and today we have a very
special guest
uh elisa polizzi who is the co-host of
the golden shadow podcast
she's going to be talking with us today
about rising feminine archetypes
and to kick us off rachel is going to
begin our session by reading a passage
from a wonderful text from a amazonian
feminist
that we all love emil paglia so with
that
rachel i'll head it over to you to open
up the session
oh i mute you darling yeah this is kind
of like a bible
this is the bible around here anybody
who has been picked up this book we
recommend it so thanks again everybody
for coming to the first two sessions if
you were here
for the first two philosopher queen
panels and we're glad to have you at
this one and
if this is your first time welcome to
philosopher queens
so i'm going to read a little passage
and then we are going to get the floor
to alyssa the
demigod is arrested
interrogated mocked
imprisoned he offers no resistance
mildly yielding to his prosecutors
his followers like saint peter escape
when their chains
magically fall off
beautiful thanks rachel okay so
like many of the other snow sessions
today we are going to have about half an
hour of conversation
uh with lisa and then we're going to
move to q a with the audience
if you have questions you can put them
into the chat and uh we will call on you
and you can mute yourself and engage and
guide a lot dialogue with with any of us
here
um hosting either rachel or myself or
alyssa
and with that welcome melissa it's so
good to have you here today
thank you so much for having me it was
so awesome
to have you at the first panel and i
felt like it was it was so charged
just to kind of open up the whole
conversation about the philosopher
queens and
rising feminine archetypes and we
immediately just started digging into
um concepts of of the thule and feminine
and i'm
really excited to hear you talk about um
like feminine leadership
and some of the aspects of that um but
just to start us
off would you like to kind of give us
some context for your for your
background
sure um i i presently work a lot with
young in-depth psychology um in in my
personal work
um i work one-on-one with clients and
teach classes and workshops kind of
based around
shadow work and dreams mythology
archetype symbolism kind of diving into
these deeper levels of consciousness
and to me kind of exploring the feminine
archetype is
important for us to understand these
aspects of our psychology that we may
not be as present to or what's happening
in the inner and outer world so i'm
coming from that place
both kind of tapping into the psychic
dynamic the spiritual dynamic the
cultural dynamic and trying to bridge
all of those together
um so you'll see me speak about that
through my client work also on my
podcast
and yeah a little bit about what i do
wonderful so just to start us off
what what really comes forth for you
when you were thinking about what to
bring for
philosopher queens what were the
archetypes that like came to your mind
and could you tell us a little bit about
about that sure
um i really wanted to launch off today's
conversation by talking about the
archetype of the matriarch
um and i think that's something that
sort of collectively
we sense is rising in um both
inside of individuals but also in the
collective sphere
this is when we think about the
matriarch we're tapping into
the feminine principled leadership
responsibility wisdom
coming from not just in inherently women
but from a more
feminine disposition in our own minds so
that that archetype of the matriarch can
be tapped into no matter who the
individual
is um and that feminine principle is
really about
enduring and containing it's about
holding um
patience sort of this gestating um that
more
emotional depth connection that
doesn't maybe jump as much to like that
logos principle of
rationale and logic but i think the
matriarch actually
stands very interestingly in both realms
of
of kind of mixing that that more eros
emotional
relational principle with the logos
principle because she's
she has to be so tapped into how others
are communicating and what they're
thinking to be able to be in that
leadership place that she kind of weaves
between those different places in this
really sort of beautiful harmonious way
so the matriarch was something that i
was hoping we could really dive into
because partially i think
uh the philosopher queen the archetype
of the philosopher queen is
a powerful matriarch figure um and
something that i think you're both
cultivating in this space
yeah definitely and i think you know for
the in the first session
i i talked about how i had an acid trip
and um i had this like singularity
moment where i was like becoming
my my mother and um i think that that's
something
uh moving from i guess the maiden and i
don't know if that would be the
archetype that you would
you would talk about um in a youngin
sense but moving from being like the
young woman
into the matriarchal figure especially
now
where there's different ideas of what
the what the feminine path is
like there's a sense of female
leadership as a as you would go into
politics or into career but then there's
also
actually becoming a mother and those two
paths in a very
contemporary uh sense are almost
divergent
you know to do one is almost to not be
able to do
the other and so there's a there's a
sense of
um tension that i personally feel in
terms of rising into this
this this archetype of the matriarch and
i guess i'm kind of wondering about that
that transition period
right like moving from the maiden to to
the matriarch how do we rise
into being these like queenly figures
and what is what is maybe the jungian or
kind of psychological transformation
of that yeah i think the first thing i
want to sort of call attention to
is the point you're making about kind of
like the modern woman having to choose
between
working and um kind of supporting in
in say like the business or outer realm
sometimes seems um
that it doesn't support also being a
mother or being
in the home as an example and i think
some of the most powerful matriarchs we
think about it on this
long scale of time and development of
of the human race is that the most
powerful matriarchs were
ones who juggled both of those um roles
that they might have been tribal leaders
healers medicine women they were both
mothers but they were also leaders in
their communities and
if we remember that we have that
capacity inside of us we
have the ability to tap into uh
being present to our family becoming a
mother
living that life while also doing
something um outside of that role
as well so i think it's just inherent to
um
our ability and our capabilities um as
women to really
juggle all of that because there is this
as i kind of mentioned there's this like
enduring
capacity of both sacrifice but also
replenishment that's happening in the
feminine principle
um so i think that for anyone sort of
struggling to feel if those things are
possible
i certainly think uh they are both
within our psyche and spirit we have
these deep sort of instinctual elements
that we can draw upon
the archetype of the matriarch to really
guide us through
um and then just to the other point
about the the transitional
phase of the maiden into the matriarch
i always really like to think about the
kind of next unfolding step
of the archetypal journey as being
both a point of tension because it's a
sort of trial and an initiation like
what what does it mean for the maiden
for the that young sort of
unshaped ego consciousness to move into
motherhood which is to move into
maturity it's
to to learn what the sacrifice uh will
be
as you move away from that more selfish
bubble that you've been in to
sacrifice your body as well to bring
life into this space and
um and and really being willing to face
like the challenges that come
with any of these points of transition
and understanding that
um those moments of collision and
tension are opportunities for us to grow
more deeply into just these more
realized individuals
and it is a loss in some ways you know
there's always something that we have to
leave behind as we transition from one
mode of life
into another but it's kind of um
this is our story this is really who
we're meant to be evolving growing
transforming beings rather than
kind of stagnant and stuck in a space of
of youth
um and just to kind of throw another
archetypal spin on it like those who
kind of
stay stuck in that youthful place um
kind of then step into like the puer
syndrome the peter pan the eternal child
and so that becomes its own
pathological dynamic that um we need to
be aware of so turning towards the
mother
as an opening of opportunity and growth
yeah it's really interesting because
even in the name like peter pan
it really seems to indicate that that is
something um
common in masculine development it's
interesting to be thinking about it from
the feminine context
because i mean the contemporary
situation for women is so unique
like considering our history and you
know the fact that there has been a kind
of decoupling
where you can become a matriarch in the
sense of like a leader as a woman
and never have gone through the
transformation of
of pregnancy you know and because that's
part of the initiation
right into the matriarchal is this
motherly
kind of dimension yeah um and so i i
guess i'm i'm interested in
what is like your understanding of the
kind of peter pan syndrome for
for a woman sure yeah um
they're it's sort of like classical
young terms sort of drawing on latin is
the puer and that's the boy
that's the eternal the child in the
masculine sense but the puella
is the the eternal child of the feminine
and so there's a recognition of that
certainly of when the feminine
consciousness becomes
stuck and rooted in that place and i
think
just recognizing the complexity of an
individual's
psychology is you can very outwardly
look like you've stepped into this role
of let's say the matriarch you know
you're really successful in your work
and um you know financially stable and
all these things are great but
internally there's a piece of you that
has yet to be initiated or grown
into say motherhood because there's that
that puella dynamic and
and maybe a fear of really embracing
what it means to
leave behind uh youth and
um to to understand what it means to
sacrifice
and to to bring life into this world
that you're
now solely responsible for which is a
terrifying thing to really consider i
think for many of us who have yet to
have children
so you can have this dynamic of mature
aspects
that are at a tension with um
severely um underdeveloped um more
immature aspects and so
that feminine principle kind of stuck in
that place might stay
in naivety um she might be overly
trusting
as well kind of always giving of herself
but never actually really
putting the roots down i think that's
tends to be very characteristic of the
poer and the pueblas they're they're
just floating
they're floating through life they are
scared to anchor
um scared to really connect and there's
usually
some other kind of dynamic going on
that's caused that something they may be
running from inside of themselves
but kind of really opening up to
the transformation that might come from
really rooting and anchoring
and sacrificing might actually be the
sort of medicine that's needed to
bring balance to that more immature side
so i'm hearing you use the word mother
in a literal
sense which i think is so important with
the
birth and the cycles of evolution and
archetypes and the new forms
i was wondering about the metamorphoral
woman the
the women of philosophy the women of
design the women of
internal fabric however the woman of
internal fire
the the woman giving birth to um
new forms of being yeah do you see a
metaphysical connection
between that kind of mother and
the mother giving birth on a
physical level yeah absolutely um
that feminine principle of the mother
that archetype is
purely of creation and and how does that
really become um sort of concretized
into an individual's life what are they
giving birth to what are they breathing
life into sometimes it's an actual human
being that other times it's
it's some grander project
some goal of life something at least at
this time that you're cultivating and
creating
that kind of requires that deeply
mothering
instinctual nature to to nurture it
and and bring it slowly into existence
and
it's not to say that you can't really be
who you're meant to be if you don't
have a child or something like that i
think some people know very deep
downside that that's what they're meant
for and that's what they are here to
give but there are other ways
to pass on the knowledge and insight and
the spirit
of of yourself and that can come through
the offerings
that um that that's birthed through that
creation principle so certainly really
does
happen in many other forms as well
many other forms metaphysical connection
that we're talking about like giving
birth whether
it's to uh child or current or
to a beautiful form of art and how this
is
all related to kind of this this cycle
of birth
yeah what i think of here is
this is a little dark and but this is
philosopher quaint um the
the darkness the shadow the the pain
of giving birth whether to a child
or a new current or
a new art movement or you know
even a a new project a new company
yeah the the pain and the
cycle of rebirth through that
how would you describe the metaphysical
connection in relation to the pain of
giving birth metaphorically and
literally
and how this this connected the the
shadow
yeah um i i think that we can look
towards a lot of uh mythology and
folklore and kind of
see like the vindictive angry
controlling mother where we see that
birth and creation has caused some sort
of like
manifestation of darkness in the mother
and she's no longer in balance she's no
longer the great mother she's kind of
moved into this darker place and what's
kind of happened
when that occurs is is highly really
dependent on
on the situation but often times
when i think an individual hasn't really
integrated that more
youthful maiden kind of earlier
child-like essence and they're kind of
maybe thrust into sacrifice and
archetypal motherhood there can be this
anger and this resentment
that just boils and boils in the shadow
and then eventually it starts lashing
out and that might look
like the you know the evil wicked
stepmother who's just always angry at
the
at the young princess or something like
that and if you think about that
psychologically as we often do from the
union perspective
that maiden that princess the young girl
is
the young girl inside of herself or this
the evil stepmother is the part of
herself that can manifest as bad and so
how might uh the evil stepmother be
railing against the maiden
inside of her because she maybe feels uh
that it's been lost in some way that she
she wants to stamp it out because
it doesn't feel good to have that piece
of herself anymore and there's a
desire to really want to repress it um
so i think that often when an individual
is forced into that place and it doesn't
happen as naturally and
that integration process is broken for
whatever reason
it creates all that sort of
psychological disharmony
hmm wow yeah yeah that
that's hitting me hard and i'm sure it's
hitting other people
hard that are here um i i've been
wanting to listen to your podcast
dark dark shadow um yeah go golden
shadow golden gems
yeah and shadow so when you do your
podcast do you look for
like a specific type of woman
is it um more about metaphysical
archetypes tell us about your golden
shadow podcast
sure um i run the golden shadow podcast
with my friend and collaborator aaron
rodgerson
he's here hi aaron and um i don't know
each week we kind of are thinking about
what
inspires us what kind of deep
interesting topic that we've stumbled
into and recently we did an episode on
masculinity and femininity and wanting
to really explore that from that
deeply archetypal place but also look at
the evolutionary
dynamics of of our culture and how that
plays into it and that inherently kind
of taps us into some of those classic
archetypes um and so we're sort of
circumambulating this idea of the
masculine feminine and just trying to
draw in these different pieces to kind
of
make sense of it i think that's partly
what we're doing
on our podcast we're trying to like
sense make together the two of us and we
kind of
want to invite the audience into that
conversation
nice i'm definitely gonna tune in to the
next
episode i have it in my queue so yeah
thank you
for doing this yeah
and um i wanted to kind of circle back
to what you mentioned earlier about the
sonic
yes and like so is the phonic connected
to the devouring mother are those do you
see those things as
metaphysically connected or are they
their own kind of categories
yeah i think there's a few different
ways to look at
it um to me like inherently sonic brings
up this very
underworld earth-based um kind of
wildness
and that devouring mother um we kind of
see her sort of archetypally express
through some of those characters that
one might consider
sort of sonic in nature but um
just because something sort of
underworld and dark and earthly and wild
it doesn't give it an
inherently sort of um negative
connotation it's not really pejorative
in any way
but um i think an interesting character
to sort of talk about with the sonic is
like baba yaga who's very
popular in a lot of russian sort of
slavic folklore and she's thought of as
this
wild witch woman who certainly is
devouring like she'll literally eat like
children or the hero or something like
that but she's also
life-giving um it really depends on the
fairy tale itself but you see kind of
this
nature uh of of the phonic here which is
she's she's really of the earth she's
dark
she's taps into this this energy and
this magic that kind of comes
from being an expression of of nature
itself and that can be both life-giving
and it can be destructive and so within
her we kind of see
i think the power of of the return to
that
dark earthy immensely powerful feminine
principle
and she can be devouring at times and
what kind of is learned or gained
through that principle when it's
happening but
she's also regenerative there's the
folklore of vasilisa the beautiful that
i think does a really good job of that
where
the heroine the young maiden ventures
into baba yaga's
hut and does all these tasks kind of
learn from her and comes away with this
skull that kind of lights up and shoots
fire out of its eyes and kills this
wicked evil stepsisters and the mother
and it kind of
psychologically if we look at that we
think about vasalisa learning
anger and power and that dark
primal energy from baba yaga so she's
not destroyed by her she's not devoured
but she actually
gains this this you might say golden
shadow aspect by
getting in touch with that phonic baba
yaga inside of herself she learns that
power she draws
it into her psyche and she's able to
kind of take out these
these evil figures so the phonic is is
powerful and it really
develops in all these different ways and
it can at times feel really dark and
shadowy and scary
um but it's also something that can
really tap us into a deep primal power
as well
why do you think that the sonic is
associated with the feminine
um i i definitely feel that there is
like a natural archetypal
pattern towards recognizing the sonic as
feminine because it's it's of the earth
and we see it in like
pachamama or gaia you know what is the
earth is often expressed as female and
that's not always true you can kind of
look at egyptian mythology and
the the kind of like matron goddesses
nut and she's of the sky
so it does change really depending on
the culture but for the most part
um mother nature is creation
and at her best and in its most
complexity and i think that that
principle is inherently feminine it's
life-giving and life-producing so we
kind of naturally relate to the earth
when we personify her to be
um be the kind of penultimate like a
mothering goddess and to me the phonic
is is
the expression of that as well
do you think a callisto
i know a lot of people that talk about
the kali yeah yeah yeah
they've stand in conservative circles
they get pregnant
death and civilization yeah did you
connect the
kali yuga to kalimantan
and how would you relate these to each
other yeah
um for those who maybe aren't super
familiar like kind of
in more hindu and like yogic um
ideas the you guys are like these
seasons of
of consciousness i wouldn't even call
them seasons of life they last for like
hundreds sometimes
thousands of years and currently we're
in kali yuga
which is all like about destruction and
disintegration
and um it's often characterized by war
and a lot of strife
and kali of course is this powerful
goddess of destruction
but even destruction is in itself part
of the rebirth cycle
and i think as the the feminine
principle brings
disintegration she's also kind of sowing
the seeds for new life
and i think kali yuga if we think about
that symbolically
is kind of tearing down these old frames
but in
to then purposefully like reintegrate or
regrow them or re-stabilize them and so
we have to go through these life and
death cycles and
the mothering sort of feminine principle
is what gives us the ability to
usher in the new energy or the new life
um
and it also kind of brings the
destruction as well it's kind of to me
like amoral like mother nature is amoral
she'll
bring a storm and that might you know
end a drought and things are great but
it might also bring a storm and things
are just
destroyed you don't know what's going to
happen and there's no kind of
moral drive behind it it's just like
these greater flows that are happening
that we're a part of
feel that with
[Music]
i think i think raven and i are kind of
just like we want to
talk to you more about all this this
session is too short we actually
we talked about this earlier yeah if
anybody here
wants to stay a bit longer and
talk about these kinds of things we we
welcome you
to stay a little more so
yeah um questions driven do you have
memory questions do you want to
uh the floor to the audience how are you
feeling right now i think so
we're we'll open it up to uh people in
the in the audience to
ask questions to elisa and
i wanted to add in a comment actually
that was made
by karen williams i don't know if she
wants to follow up on that karen if you
want to mute yourself
and talk about your comment but i think
it actually pointed out something
pretty critical about the differences
between
men and women and their initiation into
adulthood um
karen you're welcome to to speak to it
or i can if you if you don't want to
just like waiting a second to see if she
i'm going to read the comment because i
think it's really good
so she says in most mythologies
archetypal stories both sons
and daughters belong to the mother until
the father takes the son
or the son goes off on the hero's
adventure to find his father to be
initiated into
manhood so that points to the difference
you know that the the man that the boy
leaves to be a man
but that doesn't really illuminate what
happens
what happens with the girls perhaps with
the women and how they they are
initiated
um alexander talks about um the kind of
metaphysics of
nominology versus eventology so like the
nomad
kind of this like circular eternal thing
this like um perpetual
kind of sameness that exists within the
feminine
and the kind of difference the
difference of the masculine
how do you see the kind of uh the
stories or the archetypal dimensions of
those
those aspects or differences between the
male or the female
kind of initiation into adulthood
sure and i think actually karen and
muted herself was there anything you
wanted to add karen before
i jumped in yeah i'm here um yeah i was
just you know because i it was reminding
me of joseph campbell
and you know the hero with a thousand
faces and how
you know just um you know between
daughters and sons there's just so many
more complexities in terms of how
you know boys reach manhood uh and of
course we don't really have a lot of
initiations in in our you know
present-day culture
um but yeah
it you know and i guess even
psychologically from the time
you know we're born um that you know the
mother is the first love object uh for
both sons and daughters
and it's in in that respect it's easier
for
a son because he does not have to
transfer his love
you know the mother is the love object
and he moves on to
love another woman whereas with
daughters
um psychologically there's a huge amount
of you know
transition there because she has to
transfer the love of her mother
to the love of a man
you know so psychologically this just um
you know again a lot of
complexities involved there but um you
know um alyssa was also thinking about
the power of the matriarch and
don't you think that the just the idea
of women always being
associated with the kitchen and with
cooking
and sustenance you know when they were
uh
you know gardening you know gathering uh
and and basically providing food for the
family that it was like you know they
the
hearth was the source of and whatever
was brewing
in that cauldron and um and
just the trust involved and assuming
that
the mother knows what to cook and what's
nutritious and what's poisonous and what
you know what herbs to pick and what
what mushrooms or
herbs not not to pick um so that the
mother yeah you know she not only gives
birth but she
sustains the life of of all the men and
women in the family
hence the kitchen witch i'm assuming
that the whole
idea of the kitchen witch i actually
have one hanging in my own kitchen
you know kind of plays into that i idea
of the crone
yeah and and the matriarch as the not
only a giver of life but also a
sustainer
yeah oh thank you yeah so many wonderful
points there
um just to that first idea around the
the matriarch uh providing not just life
but also the sustenance
is i think part of the task of what the
the feminine principle does and what the
the matriarch
um that that archetypal role is is not
just to be the the crucible of life
but to also sustain life and to
to be both like an energy in a container
for that to continue and
um you know i pull a lot from like greek
mythology and we see like
the feminine goddesses being ones that
continue to provide that
that the structure of life and substance
you have you know demeter who
is like goddess of the harvest um
or hestia goddess of the hearth it's
like we see the feminine principle
in these ideas and that we tap into that
when we want to continue to hold
the home or to support the family um
you know and that doesn't only have to
mean you're doing that for a literal
family
naturally the feminine principle offers
us doing that you know in partnership
with others in our community
to our creative projects so um to really
be
within the feminine principle i think is
to learn how to juggle all these many
different
roles and expressions of it and i think
that's part of
the initiation of of the feminine
is that you you hold uh
maybe like the love of the mother but
you learn also what it means to like
love a partner
and and love a child or to love your
friend or to love
the whatever sort of project you're
bringing into existence
it's um that kind of idea
of the mother i think is that she has
this unboundless
well of of of abundance and life-giving
source to really offer
um and kind of just initiating into that
principle is not so much the masculine
idea which is the adventuring and kind
of
moving out into the unknown i think
sometimes the the feminine
sort of heroines journey is holding the
the spirit
of of of life in all its different forms
and
protecting it and nurturing it and then
passing it on
um and the masculine kind of goes out
and sort of
um kind of shapes things a little bit
differently than say the
the heroine's journey so looking at
these principles really kind of taps you
into like the complexity of just
what it means to be human in all these
different ways but really the kind of
youthful
initiation for the feminine is learning
um kind of to to let go of
of that life source kind of being so
internally informed and then
kind of expressing outwards towards um
other individuals or other situations
while also needing to sustain your own
life
kind of if we even think about it as
mother earth it's like we can't just
pull all of her resources she has to
sustain herself
so that she can also sustain everything
else that's on it and that
is the kind of powerful challenge that
she is left with
um that's what she's tasked with
um i'd like that i want to there's so
many good questions here
just one one last question
that i have i'm already familiar with
the lima aleister crowley's philosophy
yeah a bit without crowley the
the mother of abominations the
are you familiar with the verse about
the babylon goddess
the babylonian goddesses yeah the
babylonian hill the new babylon amber
sophia you're referred to as the mother
of abominations what
is your take on that
um and we're looking at things from like
the crowley's perspective i think he's
always had this
really um controversial
way of exploring dynamics
that kind of shake people up and even
just you saying like the mother of
abomination makes me think about
the principle of the feminine that's uh
not just the life giving but
like death giving as well that she comes
in and she's both creation but she
she takes away or she's kind of the
chaos principle of chaos and order
and that can make people feel really
uncomfortable they don't want to think
about
that dark destructive principle but you
think about you know a woman scorned or
a mother who's
hell bent on destruction and there's
nothing that will get in her way and so
i think like
just what that's bringing up for me with
that idea of the abomination
is that chaotic principle that the
feminine holds
as well and that's kind of the contrast
to that more orderly kind of
masculine principle and that's something
that we as
uh women or we who are tapping into the
feminine principle
need to understand because that's that's
a part of the dynamic
and if we if we don't want to understand
our own potential for
destruction or chaos or being an
abomination
um we are surely then uh to act it out
in ways
that are out of our control so i think
especially with crowley he was always
willing to push
things into a place that made people
really uncomfortable that was really
necessary really necessary just for the
collective conversation
definitely definitely both worlds here
um yeah we've been going go ahead i'm
taking some questions
um aaron's question so many good ones
here
so many good ones so yeah yeah you're
gonna take the questions or even i i
think
this is you okay so yeah um aaron
would you like to mute yourself and ask
a question
um yes can the feminine archetype
rise in our society without the
masculine archetype
descending and if uh if the matriarch
needs to rise does the patriarch need to
step down in some way or can they both
rise together in some way and what does
that look like yeah
i think from my perspective um
balance is is always the mix of both
it's the image of
the yin and yang of chaos and order kind
of dancing
the eternal dance you might say so if we
feel that things are out of balance
because there is this focus or
too much energy or power given to the
patriarch
then the matriarch does need to rise um
both
maybe in the form of women leaders which
i think
we're really seeing materialize at least
here
in the west for the first time the
potential for a woman to be in
uh in office is something that's never
happened before or we're seeing women
leaders
in these powerful places women ceos
women creators it's
holding that potential of of leadership
um in their hands while also kind of
juggling everything else
but at the same time i don't think that
that means it needs to be the
destruction
of the archetypal patriarch um
because that that to me kind of brings
imbalance
it's we need the dance of both
principles together and so
for those who maybe are too wrapped up
in um a kind of patriarchal um
space they might need to have more of
that that nurturing
um emotionally informed relationally
connected matriarchal nature to to come
in and that might be like um a call to
action
of say um our men or those who who are
more in the masculine principle
psychologically to
to invite the feminine into themselves
and work on it
uh to bring sort of wholeness to their
own psychology in that way
i think it manifests as women kind of
coming into
literal power um in in certain positions
but um i my hope would be that these
things can exist in harmony
because we really need both to to fully
express the
the balance of of of what our potential
is
beautiful i think that question leads
into
peter's really well so peter would you
like to
ask your question thank you thank you
um okay so young wrote
more about a man's anima and less about
a woman's animus i believe
uh how does a woman animus show up uh
what are the pathological ways of that
it's showing up today
uh eg erzatz animus yeah um
so just a couple of notes here that this
concept behind anima anonymous
um comes from jungian theory the idea of
anima
is that within a man there's an internal
feminine
feminine figure feminine archetype um
and
especially if you put yourself in the
context of uh
kind of 19th century europe the idea of
the internal feminine or within a woman
that there's an internal masculine is
something maybe a little controversial
things that people really weren't
talking about
at that time and so uh for young really
being this
sort of empirical phenomenological uh
scientist
you know he could see these different
dynamics manifesting in people that were
not just purely masculine or purely
feminine
no matter our gender or biology or
orientation and so
the anonymous is the masculine dynamics
within a woman
and and peter is right young tended to
write a little bit more about the anima
so the feminine and the man
but for us when we consider what the
animus
in is is that kind of um internal
uh logos principle is often what's
associated with so it's um
the ability to get more in touch with
that thinking function which is
kind of in opposition to what my what
people might consider to be like the
stereotypical
typical feminine the feeling type
emotionally informed very
um centered on relational dynamics of
keeping harmony
um the thinking function really taps us
into logic
and reason and rationality and
objectivity
and expression and communication and
doing so in a way that sometimes is
more informed by concepts or ideas
rather than if those concepts
or ideas feel good to the person or if
it makes them feel bad
so the the anonymous is our ability to
to tap into that
inner masculine inside of ourselves and
to develop
say the thinking function to to dive
into the logical
more philosophical world you might say
pathologically i think
when a woman turns away from that
function
and is overly reliant maybe on that
feeling
dynamic is that um it kind of closes you
off to one
maybe the ability to communicate very
clearly when that emotional damage
dynamic is kind of uh being stirred in a
way where you're feeling
upset want to express type of you know
anger or frustration
um the woman can or you know one who's
kind of tapped into that
more pathological anonymous um can come
off as just
not seeming very rational and i think
that's that's such a stereotype right
like you know
a woman gets really angry and she
doesn't sound logical anymore
and you know we're talking
generalizations here but
the idea is if we can tap into that
thinking function in that masculine
in everyday life and integrated into us
we can rely upon our rationality in
times of hardship and we can
rely upon it and cultivate it in times
of balance
and we just have this greater access to
our toolkit
it allows us to kind of step outside of
our internal bubble
or that which we're kind of seeing and
just the
the few constellations of the
relationships we have and we can see the
grander greater picture
we think maybe less about the nurturance
and more about what's
you know orderly or right or what's
truthful
and that can really help bring balance
to a situation where
you know someone might be driving
towards um
you know acting out in a way that feels
right but actually isn't
logically correct and so that can
certainly be a pathological
manifestation of it
um and the idea of course with all of
this is to
to to have greater access to these
pieces so that we just see more clearly
in our self better
interact with the world in a more
balanced way it's not really about
perfection but
but wholeness
wellness yeah yeah the integration
of the different sides of the self
everything from
the devouring mother to
the peter pan the child
the different types the the light
and the taboo kind of all being part of
the same thing i i like how you
discussed how all of these archetypes
are possessed by all women
and this leads me into a question that i
saw from key
earlier in the chat um
it's a pretty poetic
question and i think there might be a
lot of answers here
and i want to ask you um
or maybe maybe he could ask he um maybe
you could get into this morning do you
want to
mute yourself and ask this question
oh hi
[Music]
hello sorry guys i um
was scrolling up to find the question
and um thank you
all of you for having a really
awesome conversation i feel less
articulate than all of you right now and
my question is very short which was um
actually um based on a comment that was
made earlier so
i would like to invite manus to speak
his
comment so that i can ask the question
yeah i was asking uh
well making a comment earlier just uh
when you guys were talking about how
you know the the initiation of a woman
and in
in you know the pain of giving birth and
and
all of that kind of stuff that happens
it just made me think that
um it's it's interesting how violent any
act of creation is
uh you know whether giving birth or
breaking through and making an idea
reality pushing through barriers like an
entrepreneur
or even when a seed dies dies in the
ground and bursts to shoot
roots and leaves yeah key take it away
okay well
it i really liked the way in which that
question was
or rather the comment was asked and it
inspired
the question because i mean
i just creation is a concept that i'm
still
understanding so
with that said i kind of went to what is
creation
and then wanted to wonder about whether
the big bang was violent
that's such a massive question so many
metaphors and
poeticisms was the big of being
violent and i i would love to to hear
you talk about this in whatever way you
would like
uh sure yeah okay i'm thinking about
even the idea that in one moment
maybe there was darkness and stillness
and nothing and then suddenly from that
point of one might call destruction like
something is born something is created
something bursts into life and there's
all this tension
and energy and power that forces that
huge boom um and we're seeing like the
effects of that
literally now it's measurable in our
viewable
universe you know that there's all of
this
force and dynamicism to what happens
when
creation is really taking hold in our
life and
certainly i think the feminine
experience of of if we're looking at it
through
through birth literal birth in this case
um is
one of of discomfort and pain and
in a moment of of true like life-giving
energy that
kind of allows something to be birthed
into existence
and and that is destructive and that is
painful and that is sort of chaotic in
nature that is that feminine principle
but
um i think the power of the feminine is
to endure that
um i think i asked my mother once what
was it like
giving birth and she says well you know
when i do think about it
um it was really painful but every time
you know it was
i was going to give birth to another
child and there was four of us
it's like the pain of that she didn't
really recall it we have this ability to
kind of not like compartmentalize it
but to to hold it and integrate it back
into ourselves so that we can keep that
regenerative nature happening that she
can give
life again and again and again and not
be so traumatized by what happened the
way the body was
scarred um and that's part of that
um enduring powerful feminine
and certainly what i think we see in all
forms of creation i think
uh manus was even saying that even in
entrepreneurial dynamics
there's so much struggle and pain that's
going into that and
loss and sacrifice and um and and that's
just part of tapping
into that enduring quality that we need
to
to really have for uh for creation to
really
um to happen in our life
great i love that poetic question
um hamdi actually there's there's two
comments that kind of
dance around the same theme of like
integration of the masculine and
feminine
um so i wanted to tag in hamdi and see
if she wanted to ask
her question um did you want to unmute
yourself
yeah sure what did i write
yeah so basically i feel as if we live
in a
masculine um dominating uh
energy based society so i was wondering
if you guys
had an idea how do we integrate both
masculine
feminine energies within ourselves so
that way like
the society can become more bomb just
starts with
us oh yeah um
ideas yeah i i love your point there
because i agree i think it does start
with us as individuals
it's about um self-discernment and
personal responsibility and recognizing
our own
biases or way that we've given up our
power or what we're not tapped into
that allows us to be pulled into a
collective narrative you might say and
so if we feel that
the world is sort of being ruled by an
over domineering
masculine energy in what ways inside of
ourselves might we
invite the feminine in and that
inherently connects us
to not just a part of ourself but also
to to other individuals i think the
feminine is
she always has an eye towards um
sustaining
life inside of herself but also in
others so in the in the community in
relationships and it makes you more
compassionate and empathetic
and understanding um and that brings
your ability to
understand others um to maybe forgive
when you really don't want to
um and and so yes it really does start
with oneself
and and doing that inner contemplation
of where do you feel
out of balance within these sort of
archetypal dynamics how do you express
them
what's your relationship to it um you
know if you're feeling angry at
the more masculine energy can
you hold that tension of being upset
with it but then also not
want to throw it out or suppress it also
because that in turn just
pushes the masculine down into a dark
place um so it's this tricky dance
but it really does start with oneself um
and asking those questions
of what does my relationship to these
dynamics feel like and
you know where can i invite in more
rational
uh logic where can i bring more
structure that's the masculine but also
where can i
be more open where can i invite in
creation where can i
be more emotionally uh intuitive and
compassionate and forgiving
and understanding um and all of that
kind of helps us
really interact with the world and with
ourself in a way that i think will have
a collective
impact and kind of bring us back to a
balance
masculine energy i prefer
personally to feminine energy
and because a lot of the feminine energy
is not the transcendent feminine energy
that ellis is speaking about a lot of it
can be a
superficial mean mean girl
yeah esque very very petty
um very bright side or no side um
self-care hashtag activism but like
when they meet someone who actually
you know like has that internal flame
that we're talking about they
accuse us of i think trans or
too masculine and yeah how do you deal
with stuff like that
um you know what's interesting i've
always had people tell me that i strike
them as very masculine
and very feminine at the same time and i
i i i find that such a great compliment
um because i i try and just naturally
tap into
um you know a lot of strength and energy
and vision and being a leader and
wanting to like make things happen
and and construct things it's like my
really strong masculine side
and then i also want to be able to tap
into the realm where i'm
vulnerable and emotional and i'm
interested in creation
and that's just wanting to be fluent in
um just the dynamics of of one's
human psychology i want to be able to
kind of
roll in the masculine when it's time and
ease back into the feminine when
it feels good to me and um and i
and i find it just to be something that
allows me to have a lot of fluidity in
all different areas of my life and
um and i think makes it it makes me able
to relate just more to the world in
general because it's not just through
the
the lens of the masculine or through the
lens of the feminine it's
it's the inner play and that dynamic
kind of flowing through me
and um and if so someone says like you
know you're pretty masculine i'm like
hey thanks like
i'm that's a huge compliment to me okay
there's a really uh interesting question
from cody do you want to
meet yourself and ask your question
um yeah yeah it's kind of i couldn't
really put it into words maybe you guys
can help with it
um there seems to be like um
like the feminine is kind of like the
big metaphysical default
of like existence like we are in a womb
the earth is a woman like we are in one
and that's feminine um we're gonna die
and go down to the ooze
and just be dissolved into and that's
catholic um we have to be born
to have this conversation and that's
feminine and so the question is like is
death then
also is that inevitability of death does
that also fit i'm feminine
i'm thinking of like the sandman if
you've read that comic book in there um
death is a woman um she's awesome you
know um and she's and she's kind and
she's she does
she's kind at the moment of death um so
and then it the question is then the the
the right does masculine rise out of
that as a response to that of the fear
of that of
that is powerful if if the default is
feminine
and she has birth and death that is the
most powerful energy that
and of existence so then is the
the rise of the masculine actually a
response to that and then maybe it's
maybe it's gone too far
but um so that's just yeah kind of a big
big question there and i think
i've been probably throwing some polly
in there and she talks a lot about that
so
oh this is such a good question i think
there's so many different ways
to look at it and you can certainly say
that um
that death kind of as a as an archetypal
principle seems to
um be owned by the feminine but i i kind
of
see this as uh even maybe scaling out
like
farther layers where the principle of
depth kind of flows through masculine
and
feminine just kind of depending on the
lens that you're looking through and
the inherent dynamic of of the nature
of what is happening and you know there
are times when
death is personified as feminine or a
literal
female figure um very classically many
times as as like a masculine you know we
can think about like the
the underworld holders that of like the
devil or
of hades but there needs to be like a
feminine principle within it so
if we look at as an example um you know
the underworld being ruled by hades the
masculine
he also needs a queen and that's
persephone and
she needs to be the balance that kind of
brings more
of that uh that nurturance principle
that maybe brings the rebirth back
um as we think about it at least in
cosmology of greek mythology
that when persephone rises back up from
the underworld
she brings spring you know winter has
ended because she has come back from the
underworld and she has
been reunited with her mother demeter so
the feminine principle
is very alive in death but there's also
a masculine principle
that's alive in it too and what's like
the structure and order of
the literal levels of hell one could
look at that as a very masculine way of
looking at death
or the ways in which one must like atone
for their sin i think that's very
masculine as well
so i i kind of just see them
interplaying with each other and
um i don't know if i could make a a
direct
decision if it's one or the other but i
think kind of the ambiguity of it is
something that i i want to hold
beautiful so we've come to our hour
i am wondering
how much more time we want to want to
get rachel mentioned maybe
wanting to do a little bit more
conversation i don't know what your
constraints are um if there's more
questions i'm happy
i've got time okay so how about this
i i know a lot of people they need to go
after whatever um but if people want to
stay
maybe we could go for another 15 minutes
and
let's just let's go at it um
if anybody wants to bring something up
um
now is your your chance put it in or um
maybe there's something we haven't
mentioned here in the chat
um yeah
[Music]
let's see um and anybody feel free to
unmute yourself and then just go for it
i do have a question about um
your kind of diagnosis of like the on
the ground
tensions between young men and young
women
um as they're attempting to to date
or to like share workspace share
digital space um to collaborate together
and the um the situation
and you know i have my own view on it
right uh but it seems like it's
fraught um
wait what is your diagnosis what do you
see going on and how does that relate to
maybe some of these
bigger archetypes sure i think um
if i'm looking at this from that
symbolic sort of archetypal view
i think in many ways we're sort of
disconnected from that level
of our psychology and that expression of
that in
in culture and society where um
the sort of archetypes their
psychological principles you know
they're sort of like analogous to the
biological instincts and so there are
parts of our
of of of the psychic landscape that
inform us that image the world that
sense make the world and i think they're
inherent to us even if we're not aware
of them
but we also need to kind of be in touch
with them
and cultivate them and nurture them and
come into relationship
with it and in what ways are we doing
that in our daily life what rituals do
we have what initiations what stories do
we tell
um each other we're so sort of
disconnected
from that dynamic i think in modern life
that it leads to uh confusion in all of
these different ways where like what's
your role and what's my role and how do
i connect to you and what does this
environment
mean to us and there's something
instinctual that's driving people and
then maybe even a
social dynamic that's clashing against
it and i think just in all of those
manifestations
uh we're confused and and i think a
return to that more archetypal mind
or cultivating that in our life might be
really helpful
in in getting to know oneself better but
also being able to really orient to the
world
and each
do you other bringing back the bringing
and integrating with the mythic or the
archetypal
knowing is actually part of what could
help people
navigate the complexity of of of
interacting
yeah definitely yes i think um
ian mcgill chris kind of talks about
this as well and
is something that i think he sort of
echoes this need to sort of
return to the mythic mind um to kind of
understand
the right brain right right brain
dynamics versus the left brain
and and and how do we return to that
individually but also collectively which
you know doesn't mean that we
do um you know what we always did before
and how that was expressed but it's more
like how how can these things evolve and
how can we support their evolutions
religious expressions mythological
expressions spiritual expressions
cultural expressions um
it's so interwoven into uh just how we
understand our life and i think when
it's empty it really does
impact us in all these ways
it's interesting too because maybe
there's even a connection between
the hemispheres of the brain having
masculine or feminine characteristics
and
maybe the you know the what was it the
we need more right brain
right yeah yeah that's like kind of more
feminine
right like intuitive yeah yeah i think
that
that's definitely a way that those
things can be mapped out and looked at
as the kind of logical um
left brain which is about reason and um
kind of ordering and structure and then
maybe more of that right brain which is
like
creation and more of like this wildness
to it um so i think you can definitely
map out the masculine and feminine onto
the the hemispheres of the brain as well
so what do you think about
the ultra ultra masculine women now
the social activists and the ultra ultra
feminine
men now you know the voice as people
like to say
do you think this is a response to
what's going on right now
what what what do you think about this
extreme gender conformity from the other
end
hmm interesting um yes i think that
there's all of these manifestations of
it where there might be
um a kind of over compensation happening
maybe someone feels like there's
a need to tap into that like contra
sexual dynamic so the masculine wanting
to tap into the feminine
and because it's out of balance it's
being done in this way
that destabilizes things um and
you might then have these uh sort of
cultural and social expressions of it
that still don't seem like quite right
um
and i think it's it's every individual's
journey to really find
their their way towards balance and um
i'm very much of the mindset that
there's
a very deep part of you that really kind
of
is trying to order and bring you towards
um
kind of like what your equilibrium is
and so for those individuals who maybe
are
caught in a place where those those
aspects are manifesting and and they are
imbalanced
there's probably signs somewhere in your
dreams maybe i'm gonna have to plug
dreams because that's the big thing i'm
into unconscious expression
what's happening there um subtle things
that are
uh not as easy to pay attention to not
as um
obviously in the sphere of conscious
awareness
um because i think if if we're on one
side or the other it's still
imbalance and maybe part of that is like
we just need that collectively
for things to kind of even out but
hopefully it's not bringing that
individual
hardship or pain or or something if if
they're
kind of on the other sort of contra
sexual end of things but
um you know however someone decides to
express themselves is
ultimately up to them to decide but um
having that self-discernment to really
ensure that it's being done in a
balanced way is certainly a tool that
one really needs to hone
that's solid advice
[Laughter]
um we have a question from rob oh would
you like to
and yourself yeah um my question was
women are often celebrated for accessing
the masculine while men
are often denigrated for embodying the
feminine
and i'm curious why you think that's
happening whether you agree that it is
happening is it
and what do you make of it in terms of
archetypal balance yeah
um i think yeah definitely that's
happening and i think very
classically this is a sign of like the
imbalance of like the
the masculine dynamic as as a society
where
it feels threatening for in this case a
man to access
his feminine um you can think about a
highly generalized situation though but
you have a group of men
and one of those individuals might have
more of a feminine expression
what will those group of friends do make
fun of him
you know you know put him down because
he's being more
emotional or something like that it's
it's like a
a perpetuation of of of
individuals not feeling like they're
allowed to tap into the complexity of
expression inside of themselves and so
then we perpetuate a dynamic that
brings like collective imbalance so
i think it's certainly um an indication
that
there's an imbalance and a lot of shadow
in the masculine and it's so front and
center because we have been in more of
this like masculine age of thought
and it really is sort of going to
require that we give
space for in this case men to dive into
their feminine to express it and us to
not
kind of push back and say uh that
doesn't belong
um because that sort of flip side of not
being in touch with
the feminine expression is that the the
emotional world is sort of untapped or
when it comes out it comes out in a way
that's really
dangerous or violent or pathological so
what i would hope for is the ability for
individuals to create that environment
where they feel
safe and more vulnerable enough to
express it because we really do need
both of these dynamics both within
ourselves and also collectively
sure and there's even like i mean even
the pejoratives of masculinity are like
you're being a
yeah yeah like even the language yes
yeah i think sometimes about like the
differentiation you know trying to keep
men
this maybe goes back to cody's question
of like if
if the ground or the medium is feminine
and this there's this
hole to differentiate from the feminine
as the man
than to you know put down a man for his
association with the feminine
point out that he has not left you know
the womb
or something and uh to kind of ostracize
him for not
being being different yeah yeah
um there's there's certainly i think a
space
that's being cultivated right now where
even those who want to dive into that
are feeling like
it's it's unsafe or it's unwelcome and
there's ways in which we are
perpetuating that by just
the language that we use and someone
might think well i'm just joking like
i'm just giving him a hard time you know
but
that has an effect it has a
psychological effect and these things
carry out into the world um and they
pass on
you know from person to person or
generation to generation and so
it's about recognizing these habits and
willing to kind of
do the the unusual thing to kind of
press against um the norms and um
to allow kind of that other element in
so that we can
at least feel like we're all able to
express ourselves more fully
we have a beautiful final question okay
from brian brian would you like to meet
yourself
okay i got girls in the background here
uh
how do you set on fire the imagination
or how or
or or a template for future goddesses
how can i nourish or introduce things to
my 12 year old
daughter because she's active in the
background
[Laughter]
that's a really great question okay um
yes this is
um okay there's a few different ways
that i'm looking at this
and one is how does one create a space
in the home where uh the natural
inclinations of the feminine can be
expressed like what is she interested in
what does she want
to to cultivate and create in her own
life and how do we give
space to that how do we allow that to be
expressed what's drawing her
interests how are you
surrounding her with things that feel
that they're that they're giving energy
and life so that she can explore those
dynamics
um i think partly it's also really
helpful to think about
the nourishment of the young goddess of
you know what is she looking up to
what is um the content that she's
absorbing into our life and i just think
especially a lot with modern day and
what we're all exposed to
um social media got the internet it's
not always
um the best role model and so how do we
create
you know these things for us to to to
look up and
uh aspire to be and what are her role
models or
uh what would you like to see kind of
develop for her and sometimes
i think for individuals we find that in
someone in our life
we find it in in stories or in
mythologies
figures that really capture the mind and
imagine imagination
because part i think of developing who
we are
is wanting to know what our personal
narrative is and
and who is she becoming and and how does
she want to be
in the world and how does she relate
that to people that
she can recognize in real life but also
um
you know kind of fictionally or
mythologically
so yeah i think it's a lot about
influence and nurturance and the
environment
um and also just allowing her natural
expression to come out by
really encouraging that that creation
principle
inside and hopefully that kind of leads
to
the ability for her to tap into that
inside of herself
i'm feeling a very profound
power in this room right now
very inspirational
spark of energy
and wow yeah
beautiful thank you so much for joining
us
thank you so much for having me
incredible and i think we would love to
have you again
yay so you know maybe we'll do this
again sometime
and this was such a gift and i think
there's so much here to just like
continue to
unpack of course if you want to hear
more from melissa you can go
to the golden shadow podcast and you
hear more about archetypes and
all of that so yes any final
words um just thank you everyone
for showing up and providing all your
great questions and thank you to the
stoa and raven and rachel
um it was really lovely just to be able
to
have this discourse with everyone so
thank you very much
excellent and then uh we'll just
i'll just uh take a moment to plug some
of the stoa events
next week philosopher queens we're
having nina power
uh she is a philosopher and an academic
who has written is working on getting a
book
published right now that's about men so
it'd be really interesting to have a
very like rigorous academic female
philosopher talking about
men so that's what we're going to be
covering next week with nina
the time is gonna be earlier in the day
because she's in the uk so just watch
for that difference in the schedule
um but that'll be up on the website um
and then we also have
uh some exciting events coming up very
soon the stoa is like on fire right now
peter is like
totally tapping into his his dame on
so we have tomorrow the glass bead game
um it's kind of kind of an authentic
relating circling kind of practice
um that's going to be at noon and then
if cody is still here
or um vanus do you guys want to talk
about raw immortality
and um that event coming up on sunday
oh yeah um yeah now i've got like more
fodder for this like idea of that
death is effeminate and so it's kind of
a campfire
session for all the stowites to
you know put away all your banners and
sit around a campfire on a related topic
and we're going to try to invoke the
goddess of death and um
hold counsel with her and see what she
has to say and maybe it's uh maybe it's
a he
maybe it's genderless who knows but
we're gonna invoke it and see what
happens
yeah yes if you feel invited to that
that will be at
6 p.m eastern time on september 13th
and we have so many more things going on
um uv ivanova and mike gilland are
coming
we're gonna have alexander dugan derek
jensen brett weinstein glenn wallace
we're gonna be talking about anarchism
and community 2020
and leadership and the fourth political
theory aaron rodgerson is going to do
another
um session on metamodern masculinity so
definitely check out estoa.ca for more
events
it's going to be a wild month so
thank you all so much for your time and
attention and i look forward to seeing
those of you who join choose to join us
next week
thank you okay thank you